<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Posts on Steven&#39;s website</title>
    <link>http://localhost:1313/swbuchanan.github.io/posts/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Posts on Steven&#39;s website</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <managingEditor>placeholder@gmail.com (Steven Buchanan)</managingEditor>
    <webMaster>placeholder@gmail.com (Steven Buchanan)</webMaster>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 23 Aug 2024 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="http://localhost:1313/swbuchanan.github.io/posts/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Ancient 2-dimensional solutions to the Ricci flow</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/swbuchanan.github.io/posts/ancient-solutions/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 23 Aug 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>placeholder@gmail.com (Steven Buchanan)</author>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/swbuchanan.github.io/posts/ancient-solutions/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Here I&amp;rsquo;ll give a more technical description of the work that I&amp;rsquo;m doing.
See my other posts for a generally accessible version of the same thing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;introduction&#34;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Geometric evolution equations describe how some quantity defined on a manifold changes over time.
This is a broad idea; it applies to the description of many evolving physical systems, and for many years has allowed us to apply the theory of partial differential equations to these problems.
Solutions of certain equations provide geometric models for corresponding physical phenomena.
The shape of a stationary film of soap is the solution to an elliptic partial differential equation.
The heat equation,
$$ \frac{\partial}{\partial t} u = \Delta u,$$
which describes diffusion processes like heat spreading through an unevenly heated object, is the prototypical parabolic partial differential equation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Recently many differential equations and systems of equations - particularly parabolic systems - have been used to describe certain natural deformations of curves, surfaces, or Riemannian metrics (among other geometric objects).
Aside from direct physical applications, these theories can be applied to the problem of finding canonical or &amp;ldquo;best&amp;rdquo; metrics on Riemannian manifolds.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-ricci-flow&#34;&gt;The Ricci Flow&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The pioneering work in this direction was by Richard Hamilton in 1982.
Motivated by the work of Eells and Sampson on the harmonic map heat flow (a way of deforming arbitrary maps between manifolds into harmonic maps), Hamilton considered a &amp;ldquo;heat equation&amp;rdquo; for the metric of a Riemannian manifold.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hamilton classified all compact 3-manifolds of positive Ricci curvature by showing that, given an arbitrary Riemannian metric with positive Ricci curvature on a 3-manifold, the metric could smoothly deform to have constant curvature.
In particular, he examined the following.
Given a (compact) manifold $M$, a one-parameter family $g_t$ of Riemannian metrics on $M$ is said to evolve by the Ricci flow if
$$test$$
$$\frac{\partial}{\partial t} g_{ij} = R_{ij}$$
where $R$ is the Ricci curvature of $g(t)$.
This turns out to be a weakly parabolic system of nonlinear partial differential equations.
In particular, in the proper coordinates, this equation becomes
$$ \frac{\partial}{\partial t}g_{ij} = \Delta g_{ij} + \text{lower order terms.}  $$
The Ricci flow equation shares some important properties with the heat equation, and many other geometric quanities, including the Riemann curvature tensor, satisfy similar heat-type equations as the metric.
To such quantities we can often apply the &lt;em&gt;maximum principle&lt;/em&gt;, a far-reaching generalization of the fact that at a local maximum of a function $u(x,t)$ satisfying $u_t = u_{xx}$, the second derivative of $u$ will be negative, and thus $u_t &amp;lt; 0$, causing the maximum of $u$ to decrease over time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One example to keep in mind is the &lt;em&gt;shrinking sphere&lt;/em&gt;.
A sphere has the same positive curvature everywhere.
Since the curvature is positive, the right hand side of the Ricci flow equation is negative, so the Ricci flow will uniformly shrink the metric.
A natural question then is what happens to the flow as the sphere shrinks down to a point.
This question and related questions form the topic of singularity analysis within the study of geometric flows.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;modeling-singularities&#34;&gt;Modeling singularities&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Suppose we have a solution to the Ricci flow with finite maximal time of existence $T$.
Then at $t \to T$, the curvature of the metric goes to infinity somewhere on the manifold (or indeed everywhere, as in the case of the sphere).
The technique we use to deal with this situation is to choose a sequence of times $t_i \to T$ and a sequence of points $x_i$ converging to the point where the curvature is exploding (e.g. the points where the supremum of curvature up to time $t_i$ is attained on $M$).
Then we apply a parabolic rescaling
$$ g_\lambda(x,t) = \lambda^2 g \left( x, \frac{t}{\lambda^2} \right) $$
so that the curvature remains bounded.
It is a general property of the Ricci flow that a parabolically rescaled solution to the flow is another solution.
Assuming a lower bound on the injectivity radius, there is a compactness theorem for solutions to the Ricci flow that ensures we can take a (subsequential) limit and obtain a so-called ancient solution to the Ricci flow that tells us what the manifold looks like near the singularity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;ancient-solutions&#34;&gt;Ancient solutions&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An ancient solution to Ricci flow is a solution that is defined for all time before, say, time $t = 0$.
An example is provided by the shrinking spheres discussed before.
Any sphere has an ancestry reaching back forever, comprising larger and larger spheres as we look further backwards in time.
A more trivial example is the stationary plane: a flat metric is unchanging over time, since the right hand side of the Ricci flow equation is 0.
Certainly such a flow exists for all time, forwards and backwards.
Another important example is the &lt;em&gt;cigar&lt;/em&gt;.
It can be pictured as a tube that extends infinitely in one direction and has a rounded (though not hemispherical) tip.
The almost-flat parts of the manifold, along the cylinder, barely move under the flow, but the curved tip &amp;ldquo;burns away&amp;rdquo; as time goes on.
Explicitly, the cigar is $(\R^2, g)$, with $g$ given in geodesic polar coordinates by
$$ ds^2 + \tanh^2 s , d \theta^2. $$
The rescaling process described in the last section involves scaling the backwards time-domain of the flow to $-\infty$, so singularity models are always ancient solutions (although the converse of this isn&amp;rsquo;t true).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;classification-of-2-dimensional-ancient-solutions-and-beyond&#34;&gt;Classification of 2-dimensional ancient solutions and beyond&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We can use the maximum principle mentioned previously to show that ancient solutions have non-negative curvature.
Then by the strong maximum principle, a solution must either have strictly positive curvature everywhere or must be a quotient of the stationary plane (i.e. a flat manifold, the most trivial solution to Ricci flow).
Then the only strictly positively curved ancient solutions are the shrinking spheres, the cigars, and the King-Rosenau solutions, which are sort of like compact versions of the cigars.
This classification was achievd through various papers and somewhat technical analysis.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Certain techniques in 1-dimensional mean curvature flow (aka curve shortening flow) can be applied to Ricci flow on surfaces.
Recently, Bourni, Langford, and Tinaglia have classified the convex ancient solutions to curve shortening flow.
My project aims to re-prove the classification of ancient Ricci flows on surfaces using the more geometric methods used in this classification.
I also hope to apply some of the methods we learn to classification of solutions in higher dimensions, or possibly classification of solutions to related flows, such as the Kähler-Ricci flow.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>My research, part 3</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/swbuchanan.github.io/posts/2023-01-15-my-research-part-3/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 15 Jan 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>placeholder@gmail.com (Steven Buchanan)</author>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/swbuchanan.github.io/posts/2023-01-15-my-research-part-3/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This is the third part in a series of short articles I&amp;rsquo;m trying to write about my research.
&lt;a href=&#34;http://localhost:1313/swbuchanan.github.io/posts/2023-01-03-my-research-part-1/&#34;&gt;See the first one here.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this article, I will introduce some preliminary notions that will be necessary in describing the work that I do (and in fact they are fundamental to all research in geometry).
The two notions are these: manifolds and metric tensors.
A manifold is a mathematical structure that generalizes and makes precise the idea of &lt;em&gt;space&lt;/em&gt;.
Space is a familiar idea.
The (physical, i.e. ignoring the time dimension) space we live in is (described by) a 3-dimensional manifold.
One way to see that it is 3-dimensional is to observe that if we are at some point in space, we can fix 3 different directions, perhaps forward, left, and up, and then any direction in which it is possible for us to move is some combination of these 3 directions.&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;
(Here we are counting moving backwards along one of these chosen directions as using that direction.)
If we had only chosen 4 directions, say forward and to the right, then we could not describe any upward or downward motion in terms of these directions.
So our physical space can&amp;rsquo;t be 2 dimensional.
If we had chosen 4 directions, say forward, right, down, and a little bit up and to the left, then we have some redundancy.
We only need any 3 of these directions to describe any sort of motion we want in space.
(It&amp;rsquo;s true that if we choose to use the 3 directions: forward, right, and a little bit up and to the left, then describing motion in, say, purely the leftward direction becomes unnecessarily complicated, but the important thing is that it can in principle be done.)
So 4 directions is too many.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another example of a manifold is a sphere, which is the infinitely thin outer surface of a ball.
When one imagines a sphere, one probably imagines it sitting inside of 3-dimensional space, but the sphere itself is a 2-dimensional manifold.
This can be seen for the same reason as before: if we are on the surface of the sphere and we pick out two distinguished directions relative to our position, then we can specify any point around us using only these two directions.
For example, I could tell you that the point I&amp;rsquo;m thinking of is 3 units to my right and -3 units in front of me, if my distinguished directions happen to be &amp;ldquo;to the right&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;forward.&amp;rdquo;
Another way to phrase this same concept is by pointing out that we can specify any point on the surface of the earth with two coordinates: latitude and longitude.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The mathematically precise way to state this idea of being able to describe the manifold in terms of a certain number of coordinates is fairly technical, but it goes something like this.
In each dimension, there is a certain &amp;ldquo;default manifold&amp;rdquo; that is basically as nice as it&amp;rsquo;s possible for a manifold to be.
This is called Euclidean space.
The 1-dimensional Euclidean space is a straight line extending forever in both directions.
Then a coordinate for this space is just a number, say $x$.
This space is often just referred to as &lt;em&gt;the line&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The 2-dimensional Euclidean space is &lt;em&gt;the plane&lt;/em&gt;, extending forever in all directions.
Any point in this space has a pair of 1-dimensional coordinates $(x,y)$, where each coordinate in the pair comes from 1-dimensional Euclidean space.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The 3-dimensional Euclidean space can be imagined as the physical space that we live in extending forever in all directions.
It&amp;rsquo;s the space with 3 coordinates $(x,y,z)$ with each coordinate in the triplet coming from 1-dimensional Euclidean space.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Higher dimensional Euclidean spaces are obtained following the same pattern: simply add more coordinates.
Once we have these spaces in our hands, we can say that a manifold with possibly some other shape, like a sphere, is some mathematical object with the property that when we look very closely around a point, it looks like one of these Euclidean spaces of some dimension.
For example, the (idealized, without terrain features) surface of the earth looks like a piece of 2-dimensional Euclidean space.
Or a circle, when one zooms in closely on some point, looks just like a piece of 1-dimensional Euclidean space.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now we can ask an important question.
If we are within some manifold, say on the surface of a 2-dimensional manifold, then we look all around us and, due to what it means to be a manifold, it appears to us that we are in Euclidean space.
How exactly can we be sure that our manifold is not, in fact Euclidean space?
The two main things that differentiate one manifold from another are the &lt;em&gt;topology&lt;/em&gt; and the &lt;em&gt;geometry&lt;/em&gt;.
To oversimplify, these concepts refer respectively to the large-scale shape of the manifold and the small-scale shape.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;topology&#34;&gt;Topology&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Topology should be considered as the &amp;ldquo;lower-level&amp;rdquo; structure of a manifold.
Later we will be interested in ways that the geometry of the manifold can change over time, but the underlying topology of the manifold will generally be fixed.&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:2&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:2&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;
Topology is sometimes referred to as rubber-sheet geometry, because deforming a manifold in ways that one could deform a rubber sheet would not change the topology.
For instance, the sphere has a certain topology and spheres that are, say, larger or smaller or squished or stretched or crumpled up all have different geometries, but the same underlying spherical topology.
One way to see that the topology is different from the topology of a plane is that a sphere does not &amp;ldquo;extend forever in all directions.&amp;rdquo;
If one starts traveling in a fixed direction on a sphere, one will eventually come back to where they started.&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:3&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:3&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;
This is not true for the plane.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;footnotes&#34;&gt;Footnotes&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;footnotes&#34; role=&#34;doc-endnotes&#34;&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:1&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We do have to be just a little bit careful when choosing these directions.  For example, if we choose: forward, left, and backward, then we are unable to describe any upward or downward motion.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:2&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I doubt I&amp;rsquo;ll get around to talking about it, but I can&amp;rsquo;t resist mentioning it.
There are notions of geometric evolution that allow the toplogy of the manifold to change it a certain carefully controlled way.
The so-called Ricci flow with surgery is one famous way; analysis of this process was what led to the resolution of the Poincare conjecture.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:2&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:3&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is not really the correct way to state what I&amp;rsquo;m talking about, but it&amp;rsquo;s a better way to understand the idea.
The concept of direction on a topological manifold isn&amp;rsquo;t really well-defined in the first place (although once we endow a topological manifold with a geometric structure we can sensibly talk about direction).
The technical concept that I&amp;rsquo;m referring to is called &lt;em&gt;compactness&lt;/em&gt;, and it&amp;rsquo;s very important in many areas of mathematics.
W&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:3&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>My research, part 2</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/swbuchanan.github.io/posts/2023-01-08-my-research-part-2/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Jan 2024 21:01:30 +1100</pubDate>
      <author>placeholder@gmail.com (Steven Buchanan)</author>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/swbuchanan.github.io/posts/2023-01-08-my-research-part-2/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This is the second part in a series of short articles I&amp;rsquo;m trying to write about my research.
&lt;a href=&#34;http://localhost:1313/swbuchanan.github.io/posts/2023-01-03-my-research-part-1/&#34;&gt;See the first one here.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;research-questions-in-curve-shortening-flow&#34;&gt;Research questions in curve shortening flow&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this article, I will not be talking about my own research yet, but instead I&amp;rsquo;ll be talking about research completed by others.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Event though it isn&amp;rsquo;t the focus of my research, I want to talk about curve shortening flow since it is a particularly simple and concrete example of a geometric flow.
I also hope to give an example of what an actual research question in this field is like, since most of the time when I explain my research field I have to stay at the level of vague ideas and intuitive explanations.
This article will still be quite vague compared to the actual research papers, but at least it will be a vague explanation of a significant result in this area.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the field of geometric flows, we usually have some partial differential equation like the heat equation or the curve shortening flow equation.
It&amp;rsquo;s often easy to describe the flow without the use of an equation, but the equation is critical when it comes to actually doing mathematics.
It&amp;rsquo;s natuaral to think that equations exist as things that are to be solved, but it should be noted that solving these equations is never a major research question.
Indeed, solutions to these equations are generally easy to come by.
In the last article I linked &lt;a href=&#34;https://a.carapetis.com/csf/&#34;&gt;this website&lt;/a&gt;, which lets you observe solutions to curve shortening flow that begin with a curve that you can draw yourself.&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A solution to a geometric flow is just the initial setup consisting of a manifold and its geometry (in this case the manifold is the curve and the geometry is the shape of the curve) and then all the curves at every instant in time afterwards.
What makes these time-slices of curves a solution is that if you play the time-slices like a movie (this is what the website does for you), you see the curve move according to the curve shortening flow equation (remember that the curve shortening flow tells a curve how to change shape over time).
It could be moving in a way that satisfied some other geometric equation, or it could be moving randomly, but it&amp;rsquo;s moving according to the rule of curve shortening flow, and therefore it is a solution.
To summarize this paragraph: a solution to a geometric flow of a manifold (think about a curve) is a collection of time-slices of a manifold changing geometry (think about the curve changing shape) such that if you could play the time-slices like a movie, you would see the geometry changing over time in a way that is described by the equation associated to the geometric flow you&amp;rsquo;re thinking of.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When we have a partial differential equation, rather than just trying to solve the equation, usually a more interesting problem is to prove that any solution to the equation must have certain properties.
Or more often, that any solution with properties A, B, and C necessarily has some particular behavior, or doesn&amp;rsquo;t have some other behavior, or something to that effect.
To slightly undermine my previous point about solving the equation, occasionally we are interested in trying to construct a solution to the equation that has some certain properties or is missing some certain properties, or demonstrates that some idea is true or some other idea is false.
It also can be a challenging problem to prove that solutions to the equation always have to exist!
For instance, not every curve has a well-defined normal vector at every point (think about what happens if the curve has a &amp;ldquo;corner&amp;rdquo; somewhere).
Since the normal vector is part of the equation, not having a normal vector means that the curve shortening flow equation can&amp;rsquo;t tell the curve how to move if the curve doesn&amp;rsquo;t have a normal vector somewhere&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:2&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:2&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.
Even if we start with a curve that is completely smooth and has no corners, if we let it flow according to curve shortening flow, how do we know it won&amp;rsquo;t later on develop a corner and break the flow?
This doesn&amp;rsquo;t happen, but the fact that it doesn&amp;rsquo;t happen is a non-obvious fact requiring proof.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Okay, so we know what solutions to curve shortening flow are, and we&amp;rsquo;re interested in proving that certain types of solutions (that is, solutions with certain properties as mentioned in the previous paragraph) behave in a certain way.
As an example of this, I&amp;rsquo;ll discuss the proof of the following statement about certain solutions to the curve shortening flow.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If we begin with a curve forming a closed loop in 2-dimensional space without crossing over itself, then as the curve moves according to curve shortening flow, it will never cross over itself, but instead will shrink to a point.
Moreover, as it shrinks it will become more and more circular.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This statement is often called the &lt;em&gt;Gage-Hamilton-Grayson theorem&lt;/em&gt;.
I won&amp;rsquo;t discuss the technical details of this proof, but instead try to give a high-level understanding of what it takes to prove it.
If you would like to see technical details, &lt;a href=&#34;https://math.jhu.edu/~js/Math745/gage-hamilton.pdf&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; is the paper of Gage and Hamilton proving (part of) this result.&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:3&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:3&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some important tools are the &lt;em&gt;normal vector&lt;/em&gt; $$\mathsf N$$ that is perpendicular to the curve at a point, the &lt;em&gt;tangent vector&lt;/em&gt; $$\mathsf T$$ that is tangent to the curve at a point, and the &lt;em&gt;Frenet-Serret equations&lt;/em&gt;.
These equations give information about the spatial derivative of the normal vector in terms of the tangent vector, and the spatial derivative of the tangent vector in terms of the normal vector.
These equations also involve the curvature of the curve.
The phrase &amp;ldquo;spatial derivative&amp;rdquo; may sound confusing, but the idea to keep in mind is that when we talk about the normal or tangent vectors, we are talking about vectors that are based at some particular point on the curve.
Then the spatial derivative of the tangent vector describes how the tangent vector rotates as the point we&amp;rsquo;re looking at moves around the curve.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s very important that these equations involve the curvature.
The curvature is just the shape of the curve, so having equations like these gives us a way to prove things about the shape of the curve.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s another important idea: since the curve shortening equation&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;$$\frac{\partial}{\partial t} \gamma = \kappa \mathsf N$$&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;involves the normal vector and a &lt;em&gt;time derivative&lt;/em&gt;, and the Frenet-Serret equations involve the normal vector and a &lt;em&gt;space derivative&lt;/em&gt;, as well as information about the shape of the curve, they give us a precise way to talk about how changes in space relate to changes in time, and then apply this to the shape of the curve.
So we can get equations that describe how the shape of the curve is changing.
More specifically, using these ideas we can get a differential equation for how the curvature evolves over time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a good time to introduce another important tool that shows up very frequently in geometric analysis: the maximum principle.
There are some complicated mathematical statements I could write down to explain the maximum principle in full detail, but the basic idea is this:
as heat diffuses throughout an object, the hottest parts cool down and the coldest parts heat up.
In other words, the maximum heat is decreasing and the minimum heat is increasing.
And even in the case where this isn&amp;rsquo;t true, which is the case where we&amp;rsquo;re heating the object from the outside (or the object is losing heat to the outside - previously I was talking about a perfectly insulated object), the only places that we can look to find the new hottest parts of the object are the places where we&amp;rsquo;re introducing new heat: i.e. the edges of the object.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is true of heat diffusion, which means it is true of solutions to the heat equation.
However, there are many other differential equations that are similar enough to the heat equation that they share this property that maximums decrease and minimums increase (or just one of these two properties, but sometimes we only need one to work).
This is the basic idea that we call the maximum principle.
This fact can be proved for large classes of differential equations, and the proof is quite pleasing, but it would take too long to discuss in this post.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, when we left off three paragraphs ago, we had just found a differential equation that tells us how the curvature at any point of the curve changes over time.
Using this differential equation (and many other concepts and technical details), we can find that the ratio of the maximum curvature at any point on the curve to the minimum curvature at any point of the curve goes to 1 as time passes.
That is, the curvature is changing over time in such a way that the maximum curvature anywhere is equal to the minimum curvature anywhere.
The only way that can be true is if the curvature everywhere is the same, and the only way &lt;em&gt;that&lt;/em&gt; can be true is if the curve is a circle.
So, over time the curve is becoming a circle.&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:4&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:4&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Notice that it&amp;rsquo;s important that we&amp;rsquo;re talking about the &lt;em&gt;ratio&lt;/em&gt; of the maximum and minimum curvatures instead of just the maximum and minimum curvatures directly.
As the curve shrinks to a tiny circle (and eventually shrinks into nothing), the curvature increases without bound.
A tiny circle is more curved than a large one, but the ratio of the maximum and minimum curvatures on a tiny circle is still 1.
If all we knew was that the maximum and minimum curvatures were increasing without bound, this wouldn&amp;rsquo;t be enough to say that the curve is becoming circular, but the fact about the ratio approaching 1 is a stronger fact.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;footnotes&#34;&gt;Footnotes&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;footnotes&#34; role=&#34;doc-endnotes&#34;&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:1&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Technically the website will show approximations of solutions, but the point that solutions are easy to come by still stands.
Precisely, one example of a solution is $$\gamma(x,t) = (\sqrt{9 - 2t} \cos x, \sqrt{9 - 2t} \sin x).$$
The curve described by this equation (which, by necessity, tells us how the curve looks at each time-slice) looks like a circle with initial radius 3 that is shrinking inwards.
If you could draw a perfect circle on the website (and if the website could actually process a perfect circle), this equation describes what you would see.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:2&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Don&amp;rsquo;t worry, there&amp;rsquo;s a way to fix this problem, and the curve shortening flow still works even if the curve you start with has sharp corners.
(But worse things can happen too.)&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:2&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:3&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To be completely accurate, Gage and Hamilton proved the result under the additional assumption that the curve you start with is &lt;em&gt;convex&lt;/em&gt;, meaning that if you travel around the curve in a counterclockwise direction, you can only turn to the left (or go straight for a while).
Later, Grayson proved that if you start with an arbitrary curve that doesn&amp;rsquo;t intersect itself, eventually it will &lt;em&gt;become&lt;/em&gt; convex without ever intersecting itself.
Together these two results prove the result we stated.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:3&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:4&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Although it&amp;rsquo;s becoming a circle that shrinks to nothing!
That&amp;rsquo;s why it&amp;rsquo;s important that we&amp;rsquo;re talking about the &lt;em&gt;ratio&lt;/em&gt; of the maximum to minimum curvatures, and not just the maximum and minimum curvatures themselves.
The maximum curvature and minimum curvature are both going to infinity as the curve shrinks - because a tiny circle has higher curvature than a big circle.
When things go to infinity they become hard to describe mathematically.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:4&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>My research, part 1</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/swbuchanan.github.io/posts/2023-01-03-my-research-part-1/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Jan 2024 21:01:30 +1100</pubDate>
      <author>placeholder@gmail.com (Steven Buchanan)</author>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/swbuchanan.github.io/posts/2023-01-03-my-research-part-1/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I study a particular type of solution to a particular &lt;em&gt;geometric evolution equation&lt;/em&gt;.
A geometric evolution equation describes how a mathematical object called a manifold (a simple line or a sphere is an example of a manifold) changes shape over time.
What makes the evolution geometric is that the particular way in which the manifold changes depends on the shape, i.e. the geometry, of the manifold at any point in time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This may sound complicated, and indeed it often is, but we can get a good feel for the topic by looking at some simple examples.
One simple geometric evolution equation describes a type of process that everyone will be familiar with: the diffusion of heat through an object.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-heat-equation&#34;&gt;The heat equation&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Suppose we have a wire&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; that has been unevenly heated.
We color the hot parts of the wire red, and the cold parts of the wire blue.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://localhost:1313/swbuchanan.github.io/swbuchanan.github.io/my_research_part_1_graphic1.png&#34;
    alt=&#34;alt text string&#34; width=&#34;auto&#34;&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We can visualize the distribution of heat throughout the wire by a graph, so the higher the graph is above a point on the wire, the hotter the point on the wire is.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://localhost:1313/swbuchanan.github.io/swbuchanan.github.io/my_research_part_1_graphic2.png&#34;
    alt=&#34;alt text string&#34; width=&#34;auto&#34;&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, if we allow time to pass, the heat will rapidly diffuse throughout the wire, and the graph will change correspondingly (we are mostly interested in how the graph changes).
Notice that in some places on the wire, there were points with a lot of heat surrounded by areas with relatively little (as well as points of relatively low temperature compared to their surroundings).
The temperature changed at these points much quicker than it did at points whose temperature was close, on average, to the temperature of the surrounding areas.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://localhost:1313/swbuchanan.github.io/swbuchanan.github.io/my_research_part_1_graphic3.png&#34;
    alt=&#34;alt text string&#34; width=&#34;auto&#34;&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So it seems like a general rule for heat diffusion is that the greater the temperature differential with surrounding areas, the faster the diffusion.
Not too complicated.
It&amp;rsquo;s important to notice that temperature differential between a point and the surrounding areas is reflected in the geometry of the graph!
Points like this show up in the graph as sharp spikes.
So as the temperature diffuses over time, we see that the spikier parts of the graph diffuse away relatively fast.
The mathematical way to identify spikiness of a graph is with the (spatial) second derivative.
I won&amp;rsquo;t go into detail about derivatives, but it suffices to say that the magnitude of the second derivative is highest at the peaks and valleys of the graph, and lowest at the points in between.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This idea gives us the &lt;em&gt;heat equation&lt;/em&gt;, the simplest model of heat diffusion.
The equation looks like this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;$$\frac{\partial}{\partial t} f = \Delta f,$$&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;where $f$ is the function that describes whatever heat distribution the wire has (it&amp;rsquo;s the equation we would use to make the graph).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Don&amp;rsquo;t panic if you&amp;rsquo;re not familar with the notation!
This equation says mathematically exactly what we observed before about how heat diffusion works.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The left hand side is the time derivative of $f$, which by definition describes how $f$ changes over time.
The right hand side is the (spatial) second derivative of $f$, which as we remarked before just tells us how sharp the graph is at a given point.
So if we interpret this equation into English, all it says is that the temperature of the wire is going to change over time, and if a point is surrounded by lower temperature, the temperature will decrease at a rate proportional to how much lower the surrounding temperature is (a corresponding statement holds for points surrounded by areas of higher temperature).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;geometric-evolution-equations&#34;&gt;Geometric evolution equations&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now let&amp;rsquo;s forget about the wire and any physical interpretation of heat diffusion, and just think about the graph changing over time according to the heat equation.
What we have is a 1-dimensional manifold (the line that forms the graph) with some geometry (the way that the line curves) and a partial differential equation telling us how the geometry of the manifold changes over time according to the geometry that it already has at a given time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is the idea of a geometric evolution equation.
We start with a manifold that has some geometry&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:2&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:2&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; to describe how it&amp;rsquo;s shaped.
Then we have some differential equation that looks at how the manifold is shaped at a certain point, and tells the manifold to change over time in some way depending on that geometry.
When the manifold moves according to one of these geometric evolution equations, we have a &lt;em&gt;geometric flow&lt;/em&gt;.
There are many different ways we can tell the manifold to move based on its geometry.
These different flows have varying degrees of simplicity, usefulness, and physicality.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In general, manifolds can have any dimension.
In higher dimensions, there are more directions in which a manifold can curve, which means that it is more complicated to describe the geometry of a manifold at a certain point.
To describe the geometry, we use an object called a &lt;em&gt;tensor field&lt;/em&gt;.
A future post will be about abstract manifolds and the tensors that we use to describe their geometry.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-curve-shortening-flow&#34;&gt;The curve shortening flow&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before moving on to that topic, however, we will examine a geometric flow in a situation that is simple enough that we don&amp;rsquo;t need the language of manifolds and tensors to describe it (although we could talk about this situation in those terms if we were so inclined).
The flow we will examine is called the &lt;em&gt;curve shortening flow&lt;/em&gt;, and watching it in action might remind you of the diffusion of heat.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A cool interactive demonstration of the curve shortening flow can be found &lt;a href=&#34;https://a.carapetis.com/csf/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; and I recommend playing with this as you read the remainder of the post.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To define the curve shortening flow, start with a curve sitting in 2 dimensions:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://localhost:1313/swbuchanan.github.io/swbuchanan.github.io/my_research_part_1_graphic4.png&#34;
    alt=&#34;alt text string&#34; width=&#34;auto&#34;&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At each point on this curve, consider the direction that is perpendicular to the curve at that point:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://localhost:1313/swbuchanan.github.io/swbuchanan.github.io/my_research_part_1_graphic5.png&#34;
    alt=&#34;alt text string&#34; width=&#34;auto&#34;&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(Only a few arrows are drawn to illustrate the principle, but at any point on the curve we could draw such an arrow.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These arrows are called &lt;em&gt;normal vectors&lt;/em&gt;.
For a 1-dimensional curve sitting inside 2-dimensional space, the only geometric information available at a point is a single number describing the curvature at that point.
If the curvature at a point is 0, it means that the curve looks like a flat line in a small area around that point.
If the curvature is positive, it means that the curve is turning to the left from the perspective of someone moving around the curve counterclockwise.
The curvature is negative at points where the curve is curving to the right from the same perspective.
More positive or more negative curvatures mean that the curve is turning more sharply to the left or right (before we talked about &amp;ldquo;spikiness&amp;rdquo; of a graph, which is basically all we&amp;rsquo;re talking about here, but it&amp;rsquo;s in a more general context since this figure isn&amp;rsquo;t a graph of any function&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:3&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:3&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://localhost:1313/swbuchanan.github.io/swbuchanan.github.io/my_research_part_1_graphic6.png&#34;
    alt=&#34;alt text string&#34; width=&#34;auto&#34;&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So at every point along the curve, we have a normal vector that points in a certain direction, and we have a number.
The curve shortening flow says that every point of the curve will move in the direction of the normal vector at a speed equal to the curvature at that point.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So if we consider the curve shortening flow applied to our curve from before, some points will move inwards quickly or slowly, and some will move outwards quickly or slowly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://localhost:1313/swbuchanan.github.io/swbuchanan.github.io/my_research_part_1_graphic7.png&#34;
    alt=&#34;alt text string&#34; width=&#34;auto&#34;&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Notice that some points move in the opposite direction of the normal vector.
This is because the curvature is negative at those points, so they move in the direction of the normal vector with negative speed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The differential equation to describe the curve shortening flow looks like this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;$$\frac{\partial}{\partial t} \gamma = \kappa \mathsf N.$$&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here $\gamma$ is the function that describes the curve, $\kappa$ is curvature, and $\mathsf N$ is the normal vector.
This means that $\kappa \mathsf N$ is a vector that points in the direction of $\mathsf N$ and has length equal to $\kappa$: exactly the vector that should describe how points move under this flow.
So this equation has a similar form as the heat equation.
On the left hand side we have the time derivative of the curve.
That is, the left hand side is referring to how the curve changes over time.
The right hand side, as mentioned already, is a vector pointing perpendicularly to the curve with length equal to the curvature.
So the equation says that the curve will change over time by moving in the normal direction with curvature speed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What does mathematical research relating to such an equation look like?
Good question!
That is the subject of the next post.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://localhost:1313/swbuchanan.github.io/posts/2023-01-08-my-research-part-2/&#34;&gt;Next post: mathematical research on curve shortening flow&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;footnotes&#34;&gt;Footnotes&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;footnotes&#34; role=&#34;doc-endnotes&#34;&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:1&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For technical reasons, the wire is infinitely long and perfectly insulated.  Not very reasonable physical assumptions, but a precise understanding of an oversimplified situation is very frequently much more valuable than a vague understanding of a real situation.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:2&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the case of the graph, we can see the geometry by calculating the second derivative, or just by looking at the shape of the graph, since it&amp;rsquo;s drawn out for us.
For an abstract manifold, we don&amp;rsquo;t have this luxury; in general a manifold is not sitting inside a larger space the way that the graph sits inside the larger space of the plane on which the graph is drawn.
We need other tools to describe the geometry of abstract manifolds.
This is where the &lt;em&gt;metric tensor&lt;/em&gt; comes in.
Hopefully I&amp;rsquo;ll have another post on this topic soon.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:2&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:3&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, this figure does have an important property that it is &lt;em&gt;locally&lt;/em&gt; a graph!  If you choose a point on the curve and only look at a small region of the curve around that point, you may notice that this region could be described using a graph of some function.  However, since there isn&amp;rsquo;t a single way to choose this function, this notion of curvature is genuinely different from the second derivative of a graph (but it&amp;rsquo;s analogous)!&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:3&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
